The following content is provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
Let's go ahead and start.
Good afternoon, everyone.
My name is Neema Nassir.
I'm a postdoctoral associate at Transit Lab, MIT.
I've been invited to give a few lectures in this course
and basically participate in delivering the course material
for this course.
I will be talking in this session and in the next session
on short-range planning practice.
And then I'll be back again in April
in four sessions in April, lecture number 13, 14, 15,
and 16 dealing with vehicle scheduling,
crew scheduling, network and route structure,
and high ridership corridors.
So let's go ahead and start.
In this session, we're going to talk about short-range planning
practice.
And basically, I will give a brief set of definition
and concepts and introduction to the planning activities
that are usually made at transit authorities in the US
and also worldwide.
And then we will briefly talk about the measures and standards
and guidelines that are published and used
by transit agencies to plan their service based on those.
Then we will also talk about current practice
and critique of the existing systems.
Probably, we will cover item one and some material
on item two this week.
And then the rest will actually be delivered to you
in our session next Tuesday.
So the planning decisions and planning activities
that are usually done at the transportation planning
agencies and public transport planning agencies
usually can be classified into four different type of decisions,
depending on frequency of decision making
and the need for making decisions.
And the scope of decisions, the scope of changes
that are related to the decisions that are made
with each activity, these planning activities
are divided into four different classes.
Long-range planning activities, medium-range, short-range,
and control.
Long-range planning activities basically
include major capital investment,
major improvements to the infrastructure, which
would include construction of a new station, a new rail line,
a new busway to the system.
Or it could also be related to and as a result
of major institutional changes and changes
to the financial resources of the organization.
The decisions that involve long-range planning
are usually driven by political and economic considerations.
And basically, the type of analysis
and the type of planning that is done in long-range planning
activities involve projection into the future
and prediction of demand and prediction of situation
in the future.
Therefore, it requires a comprehensive analysis,
usually, for a strategic planning of interactions
between land use and changes in land use and interaction
between land use and demand in the future.
And it basically needs to capture or have an insight
into the future of the network and of the region.
The next range is basically or the next class
of planning activities is basically
the medium-range activities.
Medium-range activities include bus network structure design,
network size design and improvement,
fleet size, fair policy, and technology.
It basically involves incremental or medium improvement
to the system and to the transit service.
One point that I need to mention about the long-range
and medium-range is that these two, although really important
in the planning practice for transportation systems,
but these decisions are usually done at the upper level,
at the higher level than the transit authority.
For example, long-range decisions
are usually done in collaboration between MPOs,
metropolitan planning organizations,
state departments of transportation,
and transit authorities.
So transit authority is not the final decision-maker
in that case, and it needs close interaction
and close collaboration with the higher-level organizations
and governmental agencies to make the final decisions.
So that's about the long-range.
Medium-range is also somehow similar.
It usually, for example, decisions
that are related to the network structure,
although there is a lot of interesting research going on
in universities that deals with optimization
of network design and optimization
of the structure of the network,
because what happens in practice is that usually
in the networks that we live and in current cities,
the actual layout and structure of the network
is already given.
And it's usually rare or impossible
that we start from scratch and start to design a network
from scratch to begin with.
So therefore, what we usually observe
is incremental changes to the network addition
or elimination of some routes from the service
and basically decisions that are related to that.
Yes, please.
In terms of fleet size, could that come
as a request from the agencies?
An agency says, between the bus line,
it's at capacity or over capacity, we need more buses.
Could it come from a request to the higher level?
Yes, definitely, yeah.
But it eventually requires the interaction
and also the securing of funding
from the upper level governmental agencies.
So the reason that I'm explaining this is
that I like for you to understand why we are focusing
on short range decision making
and short range planning practice in this course.
That's mainly because the bulk part of activities
at transit agencies is related to short range planning
and short range decision making.
So what we mean by short range decision making
are decisions that are usually made more frequently
than a yearly basis.
And they basically entail decisions
about the structures of the route,
layout of the route, layout of the stops,
and basically decisions about the frequency
of service, timetable, and vehicle and crew scheduling.
Despite the first two classes of,
the top two classes of decision making
that are usually driven by political
and economic considerations, short range decision making
and control activities are usually basically driven
by cost optimization.
And these are basically tactical decisions
as opposed to strategic decisions
that are usually in the wrong range and median range.
So then there is real time and control decision making
which is basically usually done currently in using
like expert decision and expert activities.
There is an ongoing effort in the technology
to improve the quality of control,
ongoing research to use real time data
and improve the real time performance
by using real time control.
This includes revisions of the routes
that could be the case in reaction to incidents
and disruption situation.
It could also relate to holding this
and dispatching decisions, thank you.
That could actually be used to improve
the effective capacity of the system
by trying to regulate,
have a better frequency basically in the service.
So similar to the typical planning problem,
there are major elements in planning for public transportation
and particularly in short term
and short range decision making.
It includes data collection similar to what you guys
have done in your homework assignment number two,
collection of data on demand,
collection of data on supply and interaction of supply
and demand is an essential part to be able
to make decisions and make the basically reliable
and actionable intelligence
for the decision making process.
Then there should be like analysis
on identification of potential problems
and identification of opportunities
to improve the situation.
And then there is the creative part of design of options,
solution and strategies to address the situation.
And then typical to any economic analysis,
there would be an element of cost and benefit estimation
to be able to justify the project.
So in terms of operational planning process
or in another term, short range planning process,
there are multiple stages involved in the work.
And usually what happens is that in practice,
it is proven that the planning procedure can be decomposed
into sequential decision making processes.
And that's, although it is possible
to formulate all of these decisions
into one gigantic optimization problem
and solve it for all the decision variables
that you need to basically address.
However, the practice has shown that there's a nice way
of decomposing the process into some problems
and solve them sequentially in order to make sure
that you're satisfying all the constraints
to the accurate level and you're finding a realistic,
optimal solution for your planning practice.
Considerations regarding policy constraints
and some of the economic concerns are usually difficult
to formulate into optimization problems.
But there are guidelines, published guidelines
by governmental agencies that you can basically follow
and make sure that at least the top two level
of the decision making processes and tasks here
are basically done to the satisfactory level.
So let's go ahead and start and review these tasks.
There are lectures in this course that are dealing with
each one of these tasks and components in planning.
But in this lecture, I just briefly go over
these different components as an introductory part
of the course.
So we will have, for every optimization problem
or in this case, planning process,
you have a set of inputs, constraints, basically,
that you need to satisfy.
And then there is an objective function
that you need to optimize.
So the first component of the planning practice here
is bus route design.
This includes design of layout of the routes
and layout of the stops.
And basically the input into this task includes
constraints that are related to right of way,
roadway constraints, like if there's a river
in your network, there's this connectivity,
there are bridges, tunnels.
So these are the kind of constraints at network level
that you would like to satisfy.
And there's also demand constraints in the network
that you need to consider for this task.
Like you have a sense of what's the demand
from certain suburb to the downtown area.
And you basically would like to have a route system
that can address that demand and satisfy that demand.
Then the solution to the design component
and that task out of routes and layout of stops
that are basically resulting from the first component.
And then it will be the set of routes
and the stops will be input into the second task,
the task which is setting type timetables.
This task includes finding frequencies for the routes
and from that identifying and defining
the basically generating the timetables
based on frequencies.
There are usually considerations related to policy headways,
policy frequencies and capacity frequencies
that need to be addressed in this task.
But again, this task is also somehow dealt with
using the existing guidelines
and just satisfying these guidelines.
The input and other constraints that are considered
for this task would be level of service guidelines
and again, the demand constraints in the network.
Then from the set of timetables,
what will be resulted here is the departure times
that are scheduled for the service.
So the first two components of row one and row two
basically are dealing with satisfying the demand
and satisfying the guidelines.
But once you go beyond the first two components,
it becomes to the level that you know kind of
what's the service you want to deliver
and then you're dealing with tactical decision
how you can optimize the cost of delivering this service
and improve efficiency.
So the third row here basically deals with
the departure times that are given for all the routes
in the network and for all times of day.
And then what you need to do is how you want to
allocate your resources in terms of allocate the vehicles
to the system to make sure that that service
is going to be delivered on time.
Then so that would be the task of vehicle scheduling,
input into that task or constraints
that are running times on different segments of the route
and also the departure times that are given
from upper level decision making process
and it will eventually result into a schedule
of given buses in terms of what the specific trips
they need to serve and what's the sequence of these trips.
Then the output from that decision
with the vehicle schedules into
the task of scheduling for drivers.
This task also include input from operator
and basically work union constraints
like maximum shift hours and for example,
like break times and lunch times
and maximum separation between two shifts
and the rules and regulations that are related to that
and this task is again,
is a task of allocating resources
to minimize the cost of scheduling drivers
to deliver the service
and the result would be the schedules for the crew.
So then these decisions can be looked at
in another way too,
like we can further classify these decisions
into service planning decisions
and operational planning decisions.
Service planning decisions would be the decisions
that define service as it is perceived
and understood by public.
This is basically the part of service
that is visible to the public
and then there are decisions that are related to operations
which basically defines how operations occur
to produce the service.
This is somehow a black box to the users,
I mean to the passengers
and basically, yeah, yeah,
basically the passengers should not really care
what's the vehicle schedule
and then what's the crew schedule
that is assigned to the trip
as long as trip is being delivered as it is scheduled.
So in terms of other characteristics of these decisions,
we basically, for network design,
frequency setting, timetable development,
vehicle scheduling and crew scheduling,
there is the decisions that are involved in planning
basically starting from top to bottom,
frequency of decisions,
basically are increased
and the scope of decision making into the future
is basically become limited and smaller.
And also, the decision making in the network design,
frequency setting and timetable
is basically made based on the network design
and basically made based on guidelines and standards
and decision making on the board level,
vehicle scheduling and crew scheduling is made
usually based on optimization of cost
and then given the nature of the decision making,
the tools that are used
and the techniques that are used
for solving these planning decision making processes
are basically ranging from judgment and manual analysis
that is more dominated into computer tools
that are basically designed
to solve optimization problems for minimizing the cost.
So similar to the classical evaluation structure,
when you're dealing with planning questions
and planning projects or planning alternatives,
there's this structure that starts with goals,
objective measures and standards or guidelines.
So let's just make a quick practice
and define a goal and then define objectives for that goal
and define measures based on that
and see how a standard can be defined
to make that planning decision acceptable.
So let's define a goal.
So does anyone have any suggestion?
What is an important goal for public transportation system?
Maximize ridership?
Maximize ridership, yes.
So let's say we want to maximize ridership.
That's your research problem, right?
Yeah.
It's just the goal to that one.
Right.
So then in terms of objectives,
what would be an objective that we can define for this?
I would say probably the peak hour demand
could be one objective
or peak hour ridership in certain corridor.
Let's say peak hour ridership
per weekday, per month.
What peak hour ridership would be the objective here
and then the measure that you would define
would be peak hour ridership per weekday, per month.
And then the standard that you want to define
would be something that would also,
something that not only captures the demand side,
but also the supply of the system too.
So you would come up with probably like, I would like...
Vehicle riders for mile, for hour.
Yeah, exactly.
Or let's say like 60% of capacity.
Your standard in this case would be,
your peak hour ridership should be greater than 60%
of capacity.
So this was just an example that we tried to work out
one practice for evaluation structure.
But let me give you another example
that is actually used in the practice.
So I assume that we are considering the goal of
reliability in the transit system.
The goal of reliability would be considered
one of the main goals because
if we have a reliable public transport system,
you can secure and you can guarantee a body of demand
in your network that can rely on your transit system
and basically adapt to the lifestyle of using public transport.
And that's beneficial to the system from different perspectives.
So the objective that we can rely,
that we can define for reliability in this case
would be possibly, can you come up with some objective
that we can define with the goal of improving reliability?
On time performance, yes.
So on time performance would be the objective
and then we need to define a measure for this
to be able to measure that objective
for each one of the scenarios
and for each one of the alternative plans.
So what would be a measure for on time performance?
So let's say percentage of on time arrivals.
So we would say percentage of on time arrivals
and we would define on time arrivals
to be between zero and five minutes of a schedule.
And then the standard that many of the agencies use
to measure this would be 90 or 95% basically.
So this way the transit agency can go ahead
and evaluate the performance of the operators of the system
who basically are running some part of the service
and come back to them and say,
okay, your performance in terms of reliability
has been acceptable or not, please.
So should the standard also include something
like what is the gain over the previous standard?
So for example, if the goal was the library
for the previous phase of planning as well
and the library was somewhere around 80%
and now the goal is to achieve a 10% gain
compared to the previous one.
Right.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
So another measure would be percentage improvement
as compared to baseline.
And then the transit agency can define a standard
of at least 10% improvement to the baseline
should be required for reliability.
Thank you.
So then one other interesting thing
is the point that actually comes to mind
looking at the existing guidelines
is that on time arrivals are usually defined for zero to five.
That basically means that you consider a bus
that is late by two minutes to be on time,
but the bus that is early by one minute
is not considered to be on time.
Does anyone have any comments about this?
Why do we consider,
why we do not consider early arrivals on time?
Miss connections for people who expected
to be there at a certain time, but they left.
Yeah, yeah.
So it can be proved that based on typical assumptions
about passenger arrivals, early arrivals of buses
and service is usually more negative as late arrivals.
Let's make an example here.
For example, let's assume under uniform arrivals
of passengers, let's assume if this is my scheduled
arrivals over the axis of time,
and this is my number of passengers waiting
in the bus stop under uniform arrivals,
accumulation of passengers that are waiting at the stop.
And then what happens is that if one of these buses
are early, let's say it's basically arrives at this time.
What happens is that the amount of time
that we're saving due to this arrival
is basically less than the amount of time
that will be added to our waiting time for the next trip.
And that's because a number of people
who are experiencing this is a little higher,
number of people that are experiencing
the additional waiting time is higher
than number of people who are experiencing
the early arrival and a cut to the waiting time.
So if you compare these two areas,
that basically tells you you're basically having a loss
or having an increase in waiting time.
If your service is early.
And then the situation becomes worse
in the case that you suggested
when people are coordinating with the system.
For example, it is assumed that,
and it can actually be proven by looking at the data too,
that people make the transition to coordinated behavior
and coordination with the schedule
as the frequency of service increases.
For example, for a service that is scheduled
to be delivered every half hour or every one hour,
it is expected that passengers are coordinating
with the system and with the coordinating,
there are arrivals with the departure of the buses.
But when it comes to more frequent service
then we will have more uniform arrivals.
So in that case, what we would observe
is that passengers arrivals would resemble
something like this.
Well, it has to go up to the original case.
And then in that case, if your service is early
by five or 10 minutes,
you would have the main bulk of your passengers
who need to wait another headway basically.
So this should be actually added to your computation too.
Is there any questions about this?
Okay.
So in terms of the advantage of guidelines
in transit planning, one of the main purposes
of these guidelines is to communicate to public
the rationale and the logic behind your decision-making
and behind your allocation of resources to the system.
It also gives you a consistent and fair basis
for decision-making and it somehow gives you a tool
to justify your decisions and also a tool
to make sure that your decisions are fair
and justified in nature.
It also gives you the opportunity to balance
the improvement and the investments to the network
and gain a uniform level of service improvement
for efficient service.
So the guidelines that are existing in the literature
and in the practice basically, in the state of practice
are dealing with the design of service
and with the delivery of service.
So the design of service basically dealing with variables
that are related to spacing and density of stops,
spacing and density of trips and frequency of the service
as it is designed and as it is in the schedule.
So there are guidelines related to that
and there's also guidelines related to how you deliver
or how the transit agency delivers the design service
and how the performance actually took place.
So the main factors of service design
and service quality from the passenger's perspective
are basically reported by transit capacity
and quality of service manual
of the Transportation Research Board
and it basically includes frequency of the service
as one of the main aspects or factors
that are defining the quality of service,
waiting time, reliability and access.
This is access over time and also access over space.
So why do we again have both frequency
and waiting time in here?
So if frequency and waiting time are kind of interrelated,
how come there are two separate items here on the list here?
Does anyone have any suggestions about this?
So let me go ahead and explain how I understand this.
Frequency of the service is important
in terms of not only in terms of the waiting time
that could be associated with that,
but also when it comes to lower frequency system
and longer headways,
the waiting time is not a function of frequency anymore.
It basically, as we discussed,
the waiting time could actually be independent of frequency.
However, in those cases,
there is a burden of coordination
that is imposed to the passenger.
So if you have to coordinate your arrival,
for example, for your in the morning from home to work,
then there is some sort of inconvenience
that is imposed to you to basically
to make it to your coordinator the schedule.
And then waiting time is also important
because if the service is frequent,
but at different ranges of frequency,
you may experience different waiting time
if the process of arrivals of passenger
is assumed to be around the process.
Then reliability, as we discussed,
is one of the important features
and one of the important aspects of the service.
It usually is measured based on on-time arrivals of the service
and then the next aspect that is important
is access to origins and destinations.
This access can be interpreted in two ways.
We can look at access in terms of space
and in terms of time.
Access in terms of space is closeness to the bus stops
and closeness to the service from origin
and from the destination.
Access in terms of time would be a span of service
when you like to travel
and basically what is the service time
and available times of service.
So yeah, as I mentioned,
most agencies have guidelines covering a span of service.
For example, MBTA has this guideline
that for weekdays, you need to have service
from all suburbs into the CBD area
with that at least like at latest arrives at 7 a.m.
So you need to basically be able to cover
between 7 a.m. and 6 p.m.
as your services span in MBTA.
For TransLink, it's also somehow the same.
You need to basically minimum service guidelines
to ensure that 95% of trips listed
can be completed in the time span given below.
Like from any point to downtown Vancouver,
you need to have service that can be finished
by can actually arrive in downtown Vancouver by 7 a.m.
for people who like to start,
should start their work at 7 a.m.
And then there's also trips in the evening
and it basically says earliest departure time
of last transit trip in the evening
from downtown Vancouver to any town center
needs to be midnight for people who basically
would like to enjoy the nightlife in the downtown area
and then use transit to go back home.
So in terms of route design
and in terms of layout of routes and stops,
there are also guidelines that are addressing this decision.
MBTA has a policy objective to provide transit service
within walking distance, which is defined a quarter mile
of all residents that are living in area
with population densities greater than 5,000 people
per square mile.
That's basically an interesting guideline.
It considers two different variables.
One is the population density
and the other one is the density of the stops
or vicinity or walkability of transit
in areas that are populated with densities
greater than 5,000 per square mile.
So in terms of comprehensiveness objective,
TransLink basically has a very comprehensive guideline
related to basically a set of different
performance measures and goals.
Let me read from these.
At least 90% of our residents and employees
in urbanized development areas should have a walk
less than 450 meters to a bus stop.
So this is related to access over space.
98%
when they say 90% of residents and employees
basically they're looking at the person twice.
The person is on one end of resident
and on the other end of employee.
Right, yes.
So it's...
Yeah, you want to consider both ends of the trip, right?
And these percentages are a little tricky.
Sometimes they're counting the number of people,
number of residents.
Sometimes they're counting OD pairs.
Sometimes they're counting passengers.
So it's a little tricky to interpret these correctly.
So the second one basically says 98%
of all peak period transit trips
to and from downtown Vancouver should require
no more than one transfer.
That basically is 98% of people who are traveling
from and to downtown to the suburbs.
And so it may be a little difficult,
especially in the absence of AFC data,
automated fare collection system data,
it can be a little tricky to measure these objectives.
Usually what's usually done basically is people go out
and basically, and ask from transit riders
about their origins and destinations.
It's called public transit origin destination survey
that is usually done on board.
Do you have a question?
Okay.
So the second measure here relates
to connectivity in the network.
The third one is 95% of all peak period transit trips
to the nearest town center should require
no more than one transfer.
Again, this one is also related to connectivity
of the network.
And fourth one is all trips between one town center
and adjacent town centers should require no transfers.
Again, this one is a guideline on connectivity.
And then again, the last one is also on connectivity.
It basically requires that 95% of all peak period transit
trips to major regional activity centers
and gateways should require no more than two transfers.
Okay, so any questions or comments about this?
Yeah.
In terms of one connectivity between one town center
and adjacent town center,
definition of the town varies from place to place.
I know that specifically Vancouver has
rather large suburbs, like suburbs of 100,000 people,
200,000 people.
So you actually have a few municipal entities
for a large area.
But you could have areas where that condition
would be a little bit too strict if you have,
let's say the Boston area,
which has generally slightly smaller suburbs
and more suburbs to connect.
Right, yeah.
So some of these may actually be a little tricky
to measure and to quantify.
Yeah, I know better to compare.
Right.
Yeah, when I see these numbers and I try to think
about equity and the 10% that is not 450 from that.
Yeah.
Right.
About 5% of it.
So how do you navigate these numbers
in the face of enough equity?
Right, this is a really good point.
Some of these percentages, I think,
are related to random variables.
And those are somehow acceptable
because that's when you try to define
a confidence interval.
But when it comes to cases like this,
it is not a random variable anymore.
It's basically like a special variable
that is constantly requires,
like a certain amount of connections
to the downtown area, right?
So that may be one of the loopholes of this guideline.
That's a really good point.
And because one may argue that if 95% of my OD pairs
are connected with the minimum connectivity requirement,
what about the rest of 5%?
Does it mean that all people who live in that 5% area
will have to go through the unacceptable
connectivity situation?
So that's a valid point.
And thank you for bringing that up.
Right.
Does they correctly achieve these goals
as you kind of blocked the difficulty?
Right.
Yeah, well, these are basically,
these are usually for projects and plans
that are being proposed
for like a small start projects
or for improvement plans.
So I think what they try to do is to make sure
that the ones that are being accepted
and being implemented would satisfy this.
But I'm not really sure if the existing network
satisfy all these conditions or not.
Sorry, is transit the name of the agency that does?
Yes, right.
Yeah, right.
Okay, so any other questions?
So then TransLink guideline on root design
and is very interesting too.
They have like really interesting logic
to validate the design and the improvements
that are proposed for root design.
So what it says is that deviations
from the most direct route must have walking time savings
for customers on the added route section
greater than the increase in total travel time
for true passengers.
So does anyone have any interpretation,
quick interpretation on this guideline?
The only reason I do it is there's a major destination
where people are on the right-hand block
of the route, otherwise people are going straight.
And what would be the aggregate time savings
for people on the left-hand block?
The second or last stop on the route,
maybe you make that deviation
in order for people on the left-hand block
to be less than the traffic.
Right, yeah.
Right, you had a comment too?
So if you look at the problem or look at the situation
from the perspective of system
and from the perspective of total travel time
in the system, what they basically are requiring
is that, for example, let's assume that I have a suburb here
and then this is my downtown area
and there's a route here that has multiple stops
and then there's another suburb here
which in the original plan is being served by this route.
However, it requires a walking link to different stops.
What this guideline basically requires
is that if the total travel time
for all passengers who are traveling from here to here
and for all that are traveling from here to here
is going to be increased, then you cannot justify
an additional detour here to serve this area.
Meaning that if the total travel time saving
that is done on the walking time of these people
is not as much as total increase in travel time of people
that are traveling from this suburb to this suburb,
then you cannot justify the design or the reroute.
Okay.
So in terms of guidelines related to a schedule
and guidelines related to frequency and timetable,
we basically, in practice, there are two main components,
component that is related to the policy of design
and components that is related to the crowding situation.
Policy of design basically dictate a minimum headway
or basically a minimum frequency
or a maximum headway for the service
and that's basically the case
when there's no crowding situation.
However, in the main corridors and in peak directions,
we usually would go beyond the service of policy headway
because we need to accommodate the demand
and that's basically how the maximum passenger
crowding guides come into play.
So in terms of the actual guideline on policy of headway
for MBTA, we have maximum headway on all local bus routes
should be 30 minutes in peak and 60 minutes at other times
for express routes, there should be at least three trips
in each peak period.
So let's discuss a little bit more about this.
Why do you think that we need to have a policy headway,
maximum policy headway?
If we are considering the demand
and if we are trying to satisfy the demand
by number of vehicles that we are assigning to the route,
then why should we care about a minimum?
Because if the demand is really low,
that person can't wait forever.
You don't have to circumnavigate.
Exactly, yeah.
Again, the equity issue and the accessibility issue
basically.
And they're also still elderly people
who don't use smartphones to coordinate the arrival
of the bus stop when the bus is coming
and you don't want to make the way indefinitely.
Right, exactly, right.
Okay, and then when it comes to considerations
related to the crowding, we have guidelines
about maximum crowding and maximum expectation of crowding
that would dictate a minimum frequency for the service.
For example, for green line, the maximum passengers
per car should be no more than 225% of the seats
in the peak period.
In the off peak, the maximum passengers
should be no more than the seated capacity
except in the central subway, which can go up to 140%.
Yeah, so here is the transit guideline,
a translate guideline on frequency objective.
It basically defines different headways
for different, based on time of days
and based on modes of transit
that the transit agencies and operators
of the system need to satisfy.
So in terms of guaranteeing that the load
and the crowding situation is addressed
in the guideline that is related to frequency,
there is some analysis that is done
to make sure that your frequency is high enough
that your crowding situation does not exceed a certain level.
Why do we care about the loads and the crowding situation?
The first reason is that we do not want to frequently
deny to board that would yield to increased travel time
and we would like to basically avoid higher dwell time
that is associated with higher number of boardings,
ally things, number of wheelchairs on board
that would eventually, again, increase the running time.
For example, in the acceptable,
in the irregular standard 45th bus,
with the acceptable load of 70 passengers are considered,
however, the average that we estimate based on our design
should not exceed 55 passengers.
So that's the case of indeterminacy
and the confidence in intervals
that we kind of allow in the analysis.
However, it's a little different with the equity issue
that you mentioned in this case
because you want to make sure that to a certain degree
of confidence your system is performing
at an acceptable crowding level.
The variability to demand could actually relate
to bulk arrivals or group arrivals
that may happen at once due to exchanges
from different service
or it could actually relate to the variability in the headway
or variability in the nature of demand based on day of week,
based on seasonality, based on the weather condition
and so on and so forth.
Then the other objective that in the guideline of transiting
is the objective of comfort
and it basically deals again with the crowding level
or the design crowding level or crowding averages
that we are basically computing as objectives
to be tested for this guideline.
As you can see again for different peak periods
and then different type of vehicles and type of service
there's published numbers in terms of the average
or computed averages for the maximum crowding levels.
So look at this numbers.
Does anyone have any, an idea why some of these numbers
are larger for example for peak 15 minutes in AM and PM peak
you would allow an average of 60 passengers onboard
however when it comes to computations of peak 30 minutes
you would only allow 55.
You won't be going left behind
because the frequency of the services
will be at that time take away maybe another hour
or plus versus another five minutes.
Right, yeah that could be one reason
that's actually yielded to this design.
Any other thoughts or suggestions?
If you have a 15 minute peak it allows you
to have one very full vehicle that sort of
would skew the averages while there in the peak
sort of moderates that.
Yeah, yeah exactly.
Yep please.
Is this like a, could be like a chicken or egg problem
where the routes where you need a peak 15 minute headway
are ones that you really expect a lot of people
or is it the other way around where you see a lot of people
and then you make it more frequent?
Right, yes right.
Well yeah that's exactly one of the considerations
in design of a frequency and design of a schedule.
So if I want to reward what Ari mentioned
if you're computing your average over 15 minutes
and you're observing and then you're computing
your average over 13 minutes
and you're observing a higher crowding level
over the accepted level then the situation
is becomes more critical if you're computing
over 30 minutes is more critical
than if you're computing over 15 minutes.
So if you observe an average of a high crowding level
for 30 minutes or for longer period
that is a sign of a higher actual average of crowding level.
If yeah, yeah maybe you explained it better.
I shouldn't have rewarded you, right?
So the other objective that TransLink covers
is basically the comfort situation.
This is one of the interesting ones
and I do not really know how it's possible
to measure this for a design.
It's probably usually being used
in evaluation of the existing service.
It basically deals with a number of minutes
that you expect from passengers to be standing,
maximum number of minutes of being standing on board.
And there's a level of compliance
that is defined for each one.
For example, you would allow no more than 95%
cases that passengers would have to stand
more than 20 minutes on the trip.
So I can imagine if you have an existing system
and if you want to measure this,
you can go out and survey these numbers
and compute averages and compute the distributions.
However, if you have a design which is not in place,
does anyone have any thoughts how you can come up
with some sort of estimation for this case?
Yeah, simulation could be one possible way of doing this.
Simulation of demand could be one possible way of doing this.
If it's a train, I saw the sky train there,
you can see where the train fills up
and then assume that everyone else,
that everyone that boards the train afterwards,
if you know how many people are boarded in QFLA.
Right, yeah.
To do that, then you can assume
that everyone is boarding after standing
and then you can see how many of them
have 20 minutes or more left on the journey
till the train gets there.
Exactly, that's a good idea.
So what you're suggesting is to generate the load profile
for the line and whenever the load is over
the seating capacity, you measure the time period on that.
So that's a good idea, right?
So in terms of for Toronto Transit Commission,
the loading standards is something like this.
For different types of vehicle,
you would allow different averages for your design.
So there is also one interesting point here.
Why do you think for low frequency service,
you would allow a lower crowding level
or a lower average ridership?
If it was that crowded, you would want to add frequency
to better serve people riding.
Right, yeah.
That could be one good answer.
The other reason that I can imagine
is that if it's a low frequency service
and if someone is denied boarding
to a low frequency service, they have to wait longer.
So we would allow a little bit of slackness in the design
so we would avoid situation like that.
Okay, so let's stop here and then we will continue
to the rest of the guidelines,
particularly with reliability of service next week.
Is there a question here?
Right.
Someone asked, is there a reason
why we use so many community examples?
Sorry?
Is there a reason why we use so many community examples?
That's a good question.
Public transportation is good.
Yeah, better, probably the closest place
that has a better public transportation.
OK.